<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://lukenathaniel.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://lukenathaniel.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-10-13T06:49:27-05:00</updated><id>http://lukenathaniel.com/</id><title>Searching for Signals - Luke Nathaniel</title><subtitle>A collection of ideas, inspiration, questions and the occasional film reference.
</subtitle><author><name>Luke Nathaniel</name><email>me@lukenathaniel.com</email></author><entry><title>The difference between advice and feedback</title><link href="http://lukenathaniel.com/2017/10/10/2017-advice-vs-feedback.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The difference between advice and feedback" /><published>2017-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://lukenathaniel.com/2017/10/10/2017-advice-vs-feedback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://lukenathaniel.com/2017/10/10/2017-advice-vs-feedback.html">&lt;p&gt;The difference between advice and feedback is something I learned from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KPRual8bJtM&quot;&gt;my late father-in-law Bill&lt;/a&gt;, a Greek immigrant with no formal education beyond third grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill had a loud voice and a heavy accent. He got right to the point and was never shy about using profanity to get there. I’m also pretty sure he spent his 95 years on this Earth having never considered what anyone wanted to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;jb_picture&quot;&gt;&lt;img itemprop=&quot;image&quot; alt=&quot;Bill Mihalopoulos - 1977&quot; src=&quot;/images/2017/08/bill-gangsta.jpg&quot; longdesc=&quot;#e9d79173&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption id=&quot;e9d79173&quot;&gt;Dimitra Mihalopoulos&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years ago I worked for a startup based in New York City. I flew there every few months but otherwise worked remotely from my home in Iowa just 3 blocks away from my in-laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since closing his restaurant in the ’80s, Bill had divided his time between visiting with his many friends and managing his handful of rental properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 90 years young he was still able to mostly handle the business himself, although a stroke and his failing vision made it harder for him to get around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Bill was unhappy about his dependence on others, he didn’t let pride slow him down. Everyone was pressed into service, including mutual friends: “I had lunch with your father-in-law last week! Then I took him to City Hall to sign permits or something.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill knew I worked from home, so at least twice a week he’d invite me over to eat. His English was really limited but if anything it made him a ruthless and efficient communicator:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill: “How’s go with you? We gotta spaghetti, you come over?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me: “I have to keep working for a while Bill, how about later?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill: “Piss on you.” (Translation: suit yourself.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More often than not, I’d make time to visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill would ambush me with correspondence the moment I sat down at his dining room table - receipts, vendor invoices, junk mail - anything he thought was worth a second look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew there were strings attached to these vitis, but I didn’t mind. Most of my days were spent hunkered down in design work, so the occasional disruption was welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And besides, I enjoyed his company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During one such working meal, Bill and I discussed his latest project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was now October, and winter was on his mind. One of his buildings had recurring problems with ice dams forming at the low side of the pitched roof. We needed to keep the drain pipe free of ice, or we could look forward to having a pond on the roof in January, along with all the problems that go with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After brainstorming and ruling out some creative alternatives - like pouring sidewalk ice-melt down the roof’s drain pipe - we agreed to just have a new commercial-grade heat tape installed by an electrician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill picked up his worn deck of playing cards, leaned back in his chair and changed the subject:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How’s go you job?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switching gears usually meant we’d discussed a topic to his satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The job was on my mind, in fact. My boss had stepped aside and I needed to fly out to meet his replacement, so another trip to NYC was on the horizon. With the growing horde of unfamiliar faces, these visits increasingly felt like the first day of school in a new town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was hesitant to confide in Bill, though. I’d once seen him offer advice before, like the time a depressed relative sat before him, anxious and nearly catatonic. Bill’s only counsel was to look up and snap “You crazy - that’s it!” before returning to his game of solitaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against my instincts, I let slip that I was a little stressed about work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill immediately sat up in his chair and nodded, putting his cards down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was caught off guard. I’m sure he’d asked me the same question a hundred times before, but now he seemed genuinely interested. So I continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The company had grown from 12 to 100+ employees in just 2 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was expected to travel to New York City more often for face time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should I move there? Could I hack it? Was I in over my head?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I carried on, asking this old man from the village what he thought about my future in the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill continued to nod attentively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His apparent concern made me a little emotional. I’d never known him to listen so patiently while anyone talked about their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could tell he had something to say so I paused:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What do you think I should do?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He leaned forward, pointing for emphasis, and spoke:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Think so…better we put the heat tape the roof next week. See they no working. Next month, maybe snow?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His eyes were wide with excitement; he couldn’t wait to get to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hey, too easy do ‘em now!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He shrugged, and then abruptly turned his attention to his playing cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, I felt better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with advice is bias. We ask other people for feedback, but then define our problems in a way that imposes parameters on it. We want other people to tell us what we want to hear, and since most people would rather “be nice” than honest, most people oblige us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people but not everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I ruminated aloud about phantom challenges and startup drama, Bill’s mind was on solving a problem someone could actually do something about. He was focused on &lt;em&gt;right now.&lt;/em&gt; My navel-gazing didn’t even warrant acknowledgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I instantly saw how pointless it was for me to worry about things beyond my control, and no advice could have driven this point home better than Bill’s comical indifference. It was the only appropriate feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think advice-seeking is a tactic people use to avoid learning small but important lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to relate cause-and-effect when you’re acting on someone’s advice. When decisions are your own they provide a closed loop: &lt;em&gt;Think. Do. Learn.&lt;/em&gt; Growth is just a matter of paying attention to feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turning on your radar is the easy part. What is not easy is finding brutal honesty, especially when &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raptitude.com/2013/04/honesty-can-be-pretty-damn-rude/&quot;&gt;lying is a regular part of being polite&lt;/a&gt;. That we call other people “blunt” says a lot about how uncomfortable the truth makes us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But being comfortable isn’t always good for you. The more we spare each other’s feelings, the more likely we are to just get the advice we want instead of the feedback we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being blunt came naturally to Bill. It would have taken too much effort to sugarcoat the truth: “No worth it,” he would have said. He didn’t stifle himself in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For others, it’s not as easy. It takes guts to give honest feedback, and it takes guts to hear it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You crazy, that’s it!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Point taken, Bill.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Luke Nathaniel</name><email>me@lukenathaniel.com</email></author><summary>The difference between advice and feedback is something I learned from my late father-in-law Bill, a Greek immigrant with no formal education beyond third grade.

Bill had a loud voice and a heavy accent. He got right to the point and was never shy about using profanity to get there. I’m also pretty sure he spent his 95 years on this Earth having never considered what anyone wanted to hear.</summary></entry></feed>
